To most of us,
snakes shout danger!
And that's a valuable instinct.
Every year, they bite
over five million people.
Some have lethal venom,
others primal aggression.
A handful have both.
Which snake is the most dangerous?
It's the one in front of you.
What are your chances?
We'll tally them up
and tell you.
World's Deadliest Snakes.
Australia.
India.
But first, Southeast Asia.
A hot spot for some
of the world's deadliest snakes.
The humid tropical rain forests
of Indonesia.
A hunting ground for one
of the biggest
and most powerful snakes
in the world.
♪ ♪
It's a reticulated python,
longer than a London bus.
No venom, but a bad temper,
350 pounds of it.
Such a colossal predator
requires a man-sized meal.
Usually hunting at night,
the python's reticulated camouflage
allows it to move around
the jungle
unnoticed in the day.
Despite its enormous size,
this giant is surprisingly active.
Even primates are
a welcome appetizer.
In the wild it can hunt anywhere,
but water helps support
its massive bulk.
It's capable of staying submerged
for up to 20 minutes.
You'll never see it coming.
These jungle streams provide
this giant python
a direct express lane
into human settlements.
Southeast Asia is home
to over 655 million people,
and many communities border
the python's rain forests.
It's not unknown for pets
to go missing,
and sometimes children.
Night gives the python
the advantage.
Cat-like eyes are optimized
for night vision.
And those pits along its snout
detect the body heat
of warm-blooded prey.
♪ ♪
Once locked in its jaws,
around 100 recurved teeth
make escape near impossible.
Squeezing so tight,
it stops their blood flowing
within minutes.
Flexible bones and ligaments
allow the python
to spread its mouth
wider than its skull.
This meal is the size
of a child.
A serious problem when a hungry
python ventures into a village.
The reticulated python's fear
and aggression factors are high,
but it's all brute strength,
without the venom.
Bites are devastating, but rare.
Unless you're a small child,
your chances of survival
are high.
When it comes to snakes,
you don't always have to be big
to be deadly.
India, China and Indonesia,
famous for coffee, tea,
and venomous reptiles.
Hidden within the leaves
are small, arboreal snakes
that terrify local farmers.
Green pit vipers.
They don't mean
to harm humans.
It's a by-product of their
incredible hunting prowess.
Like the python, they use
heat-sensing pit organs
on either side of their heads
to track warm-blooded prey
like birds and rats.
♪ ♪
That wide head houses
large venom glands
and long, hinged fangs.
Like other vipers,
their mouths
can open almost 180 degrees
to strike.
But their venom isn't
the worst of them.
Green pit vipers are dangerous
because these tree-dwellers hunt
and strike at head height.
A mistaken bite on a human
can cause bleeding
and painful swelling,
sometimes resulting
in asphyxiation and death.
They account for more snakebites
than any other group
in all of Southeast Asia.
And they have another
tag-team cousin
at work below.
There's a more venomous viper
lurking in the leaf litter.
A snake that's responsible
for several hundred snakebites
every year.
The Malayan pit viper.
Palm oil and rubber plantations
pepper the jungles
of Southeast Asia.
Great places for a snake
to hunt rodents.
Its strategy is
to bite immediately,
injecting fast-acting,
hemotoxic venom,
which causes severe pain,
extensive necrosis
and massive internal bleeding.
Its venom is so effective,
its anticoagulant properties
are being researched
as potential treatment
for stroke victims.
While its cousins,
the green pit vipers,
take care of the trees,
the Malayan pit viper
covers the ground,
lying in wait for rodents
and frogs.
Its pointed, leaf-shaped head
and mottled markings
help it blend perfectly
into the leaf litter.
Invisible.
So easy to step on.
These fangs can breach
a rubber boot.
Due to the lack of antivenom
and hospital treatment
in rural Southeast Asia,
those that survive
are often left
with dysfunctional
or amputated limbs,
which is why it's
locally nicknamed
the "axe snake."
It's time to tally up
our first contenders
for the title of the Indo-Pacific's
deadliest snake.
The pit vipers' venoms
are potent enough
to devastate limbs,
and they're quick to strike.
Yet, despite being responsible
for hundreds of thousands
of bites each year,
only 2% are fatal.
But it's more than enough
to beat the giant python
off top spot,
for now.
India.
Home to four of the world's
deadliest snakes
and nearly 1.4 billion people.
Over four times the population
of the US,
in a country smaller
than the West Coast.
A myriad of people
and a host of dangerous snakes;
a recipe for disaster.
One of the most venomous
is the common krait.
It's small, slender
and unassuming.
Yet its venom,
meant to immobilize prey,
can cause respiratory arrest
in humans.
Just one bite
can kill seven people.
Shy, docile, and slow by day.
At night,
the krait transforms
into an alert
and active hunter.
During the rainy season,
it enters homes
in search of shelter,
warmth, and reptiles.
Rolling the wrong way
could be fatal.
The common krait's bite
is so small and painless,
it feels like a mosquito bite.
In a matter of hours,
full-body paralysis sets in
and maybe death.
Many bite victims
simply never wake up.
The common krait is a problem
in India,
but there's an even more
dangerous killer
that haunts India's farmlands.
An ambush predator,
known as the lurker.
A snake that is near-impossible
to see,
until it's too late.
The highly venomous
Russell's viper.
One of the most dangerous snakes
in all of Asia.
This large, stocky,
slow-moving snake
is a master of camouflage.
Notoriously defensive,
it often holds its ground
and gets stepped on
by accident.
Not only do people
not see it,
but its strikes are so quick,
there's no time to react.
Its large, flattened head
accommodates
two long, half-inch,
hinged fangs,
which deliver huge doses
of potent cytotoxic venom.
A bite causes
excruciating pain
and begins destroying flesh.
It's a predatory masterpiece,
but what makes the Russell's viper
so dangerous
is its penchant
for entering human settlements.
Why?
They're not malicious,
they're just after rats.
Out here,
there are no hospitals,
and antivenom,
even if you can find it,
isn't always effective.
So, bites claim thousands
of limbs and lives every year.
Arch-enemy,
or valuable service provider?
Pest control.
Rodents bite back,
so the viper and its venom
have a nifty plan.
Bite......
And release.
Large glands at the back
of its head
yield enough venom
to kill over 600 mice
from a single bite.
The common krait and this,
the Russell's viper,
are considered two of
the deadliest snakes on Earth.
But how do they score
against each other?
The common krait
is reluctant to bite,
but when it does,
it injects
one of the most potently
toxic venoms in the world.
Found throughout India,
it's responsible for tens of
thousands of bites each year,
and if left untreated,
80% of its victims die.
But does the Russell's viper
have the edge?
Its venom glands are larger,
injecting higher doses
of lethal venom.
And due to its wide distribution
around India,
and highly defensive demeanor,
the Russell's viper
is responsible
for more snakebites
than any other snake in the country,
killing thousands every year.
Despite its lethal potential,
the common krait's small fangs
and low venom yield
cost it first place,
making way for the Russell's viper
to take pole position.
To find a worthy challenger,
we must travel
to the country
with the deadliest wildlife
in the world: Australia.
The land of sun, surf,
and snakes.
Here, there is a dangerous snake
for every habitat,
but one in particular is found
all across Australia.
A snake so feared,
it's simply called
the death adder.
And it's hard to spot.
Its patterns and colorations
mimic its surroundings;
dry, arid deserts,
or the undergrowth
of Australia's woodlands.
There it is.
You only notice the death adder
when it moves through the forest,
crossing roads or entering
people's backyards.
The minute it stops,
it vanishes.
It can lie in wait,
submerged in the leaf litter,
motionless,
for days at a time,
primed for an explosive attack.
But first, a trick.
Is that a worm,
or a tail?
Once inquisitive prey
is within range,
this passive hunter unleashes
the fastest strike
in Australia,
under a tenth of a second.
What makes this efficient hunter
so dangerous to humans
are its defensive strikes
on pets and people.
Innocently lying in ambush,
often stepped on by unwary hikers.
Its large, quarter-inch fangs,
swift strike and high venom yield
can inflict serious damage.
Potent, neurotoxic venom
can kill a human
within six hours.
You may make it past them...
But dogs often don't,
succumbing to bites
in just 20 minutes,
regardless of antivenom treatment.
One bite from a death adder
holds enough venom
to kill over 18 people.
And its strike is super fast
and aggressive.
But hidden in the wilds
of Australia,
hikers are the most at risk
of stepping on one,
and while many pets are killed
each year,
nearly all humans survive.
The death adder
is more defensive
and potent than the pit vipers,
but widely accessible medical care
and antivenom
costs it a higher ranking.
Thousands of miles
from the coast,
deep in the outback
of central Australia
is a snake
with a fierce reputation.
The rare and reclusive
inland taipan,
the most potently venomous snake
on the planet.
Why?
Life out here is tough.
To find food,
this large, six-foot snake
can't sit and wait,
it must hunt.
It carries highly specialized
neuro- and hemotoxic venom.
♪ ♪
If this rat gets away,
it may not see another
for days.
To make sure,
it can inject
40,000 times the amount
of venom
necessary to kill the rat.
Awesome?
Maybe not.
Just one of those bites
is enough to kill
over 100 people.
Prey suffer seizures,
paralysis, and internal bleeding,
all within seconds.
And no chance of escape.
This arid desert is
no place to dawdle.
With little shade,
temperatures can soar
over 100 degrees Fahrenheit,
but the taipan has adapted
by changing the color
of its skin.
They lighten in summer,
so as not to overheat,
and darken
during the cooler months,
to retain warmth.
For shelter, the taipan
makes good use
of any unoccupied burrows
and deep cracks
in the dry plains.
It's also the perfect place
to hide eggs.
Newborn taipans
are five times smaller
than the adults,
but also deadly.
Once free, they must
fend for themselves,
with only their venom
to protect them.
But there is one predator
that's immune to even
the taipan's bite.
They call it the mulga.
10 Feet long,
13 pounds in bulk,
it's Australia's heaviest
venomous snake.
Hence its common name,
the king brown.
It's a hunter of snakes,
with immunity to most
of Australia's most venomous,
including the smaller taipan.
♪ ♪
The king brown's venom may not be
as potent
as the taipan's,
but what it lacks in quality,
it makes up for in quantity,
injecting up to six times
more venom
in a single bite;
the largest venom yield
ever recorded.
Prey suffers hemorrhaging,
paralysis and renal failure.
Australia is home to some of
the world's most venomous snakes,
but how do they rate
against the rest?
The inland taipan
is rightly feared.
Its venom is so potent
that an untreated bite
could kill you
in less than an hour.
But this shy serpent
is relatively placid
and would rather flee
than fight,
so, bites to humans
are uncommon.
Australia is home
to over 25 million people,
but 85% of the population lives
within 30 miles of the coast,
and the inland taipan
hides out
in the middle of the remote
and desolate outback.
Nearly all that are bitten
have survived,
thanks to quick hospitalization.
Which means it may be the world's
most venomous snake,
but the inland taipan
is far from being
the Indo-Pacific's deadliest.
Perhaps the king brown
can kill you quicker?
Its venom may not be as potent
as the taipan's,
but it has a savage bite
and injects enormous amounts.
And being the most widespread
snake in Australia,
bites are much more frequent.
But thanks to localized antivenom,
deaths are rare.
Deadly enough to pip
the taipans.
The king brown
is a heavyweight,
but to find the true king
of deadly snakes,
we must travel to the jungles
of Southeast Asia.
These are the hunting grounds
for the longest venomous snake
in the world.
♪ ♪
The king cobra can stand up
and look you in the eyes.
Using up to 20 pounds
of pure muscle
to raise its body four foot
off the ground.
Like most cobras,
it can flatten its ribs,
extending the looser skin
on its neck.
This colossus can easily live
for 20 years
in the wild,
growing up to 18 foot.
Everything about the king
is large,
including its appetite
and its venom load.
One bite can kill an elephant
in just three hours;
a human, in 30 minutes.
But there's a reason
for its deadliness.
It's a voracious hunter
of other big snakes.
While known to feed on small,
venomous kraits
and other cobras,
they usually hunt down
larger species,
even giant pythons.
This 10-foot rat snake
is unaware it's being watched.
Rat snakes often cloak themselves
in the scent
of their last kill,
so other rodents are less likely
to detect them;
a scent the cobra
can easily track.
The king uses its lower jaw
to detect tiny vibrations
on the ground
to home in on its target.
It needs all the venom,
power and size it can muster.
Bad for the rat snake,
and bad for us.
16-Millimeter fangs,
like hypodermic needles,
inject 20 times more venom
than most venomous snakes
in a single bite.
Within minutes, the neurotoxins
stun the nervous system,
paralyzing the body,
shutting down lungs
and damaging brain functions,
while other toxins begin
the digestion process,
from the inside out.
The cobra's backward-facing teeth
help walk the meal down.
A 10-foot rat snake fits nicely
inside an 18-foot cobra.
The king may be the biggest
venomous killer around,
but is it the deadliest
to us?
A single bite from a king cobra
is enough to kill a human
20 times over.
Yet, despite its size
and reputation,
it's not overly aggressive.
But it doesn't hesitate
to defend itself,
biting tens of thousands
of people each year,
which, left untreated, kills
thousands across the Indo-Pacific.
The king competes
with the deadliest on every level,
but its more tolerant attitude
and reluctance to bite
costs it first place.
If the king can't conquer
top spot,
what about an entire family
of Asian cobras?
There are 12 species of cobra
found throughout
the Indo-Pacific,
and they exact a terrible toll
on the people that live here.
Some can spit their venom,
while others rely
on their size,
cunning, and deadly bite.
The monocled cobra is found
across Southeast Asia,
as far west as Thailand.
This large six-foot snake
hunts rodents
around open fields
and rice paddies,
making human contact inevitable.
With a short temper,
it's aggressively defensive.
It gets its name
from the large circle
on the back of its hood,
and its highly potent
neurotoxic venom
is some of the fastest acting
in the world.
But one of Asia's Big Four
is found throughout
the Indian Subcontinent.
It thrives along the edges
of forests,
fields and villages,
especially near water.
Not one, but two circles;
the spectacled cobra.
The spectacled cobra
is highly alert
to movement,
often striking out,
and highly venomous.
Its hood is deeply cupped.
This cobra puts on
a real show.
Those spectacled eyes
are distinct.
Know your enemy.
It's drawn to the edge
of villages
in its search for food.
A bite not only eats away
at your flesh,
but also causes
full-body paralysis,
crippling your ability
to breathe,
within hours.
With food on tap
in and around human dwellings,
the spectacled cobra
is a familiar face.
♪ ♪
This cobra is so feared,
it's worthy of Hindu deity.
But is it deadly enough
to take top spot?
The monocled and
spectacled cobras
have bites to match
their barks.
And death comes quickly.
They are intolerant
and strike on movement,
but what makes them
really deadly
are their numbers.
Unlike the king,
they are found
all across India
and Southeast Asia,
living among
billions of people,
which makes them responsible
for hundreds of thousands
of bites each year.
And with limited antivenom
and hospital care,
many tens of thousands
of their victims die.
Making the monocled
and spectacled cobras
the deadliest snakes
in Asia...
For now.
It will take a serious
contender
to knock the cobras
off the top spot.
But maybe the second most
venomous snake
in the world could do it.
Down under,
many of the deadliest
look alike.
Taipan?
Mulga?
No.
This is an eastern brown.
Responsible for more
snakebite fatalities
in Australia than any other.
Like the taipans,
their venom
has evolved to kill
fast-moving prey quickly.
They, too, are very fast,
actively chasing down
their prey.
But what makes this snake
so dangerous
is that it thrives
in towns and cities
all across the east coast,
in the most populated areas
of Australia.
It can squeeze its narrow,
five-foot, slender body
through tiny gaps in doorways
of homes and sheds.
Like many others
on the leaderboard,
they're only here for the rats,
but that often means
they face us.
If disturbed,
it reveals a calling card:
a signature "S"
for maximum strike force.
That strike comes
at 40 miles an hour,
often with a gaping mouth
to compensate for its short,
fixed fangs,
which usually means
a painless bite
and one that's difficult
to see.
Yet each bite delivers a small
but deadly venom cocktail,
causing progressive paralysis
and uncontrollable bleeding.
Victims can collapse
within minutes,
and if left untreated,
they could be dead
in under half an hour.
The eastern brown's venom
is so toxic,
not even antivenom
can reverse the effects.
It has a short fuse
and attacks with little warning,
making it responsible
for thousands of bites every year.
In the last decade,
60% of Australia's snakebite
deaths were attributed to them.
They have the venom,
the defensiveness and the opportunity,
but thanks to quick
hospitalization,
they just miss out
on the lead.
To be the deadliest,
a snake needs aggression,
a deadly bite, opportunity,
and human vulnerability.
For that, we need
to return to India.
India is home to nearly
one and a half billion people.
Many of which live and work
in the densely populated
rural districts.
Men, women and children
share this open farmland
with four of the world's
deadliest snakes.
We've met three of them.
And each year, close to 50,000
people die here
from snakebites.
That's the equivalent of a town
being wiped out every year.
And most of those deaths
are from the fourth.
The saw-scaled viper.
Many snakes offer
a clear warning
to stay away,
but this one
is a born deceiver.
At only 12 inches long,
the saw-scaled viper
may be small,
but it packs
a serious punch.
Its venom is many times
more potent
than any cobra.
And being highly aggressive,
it strikes readily.
Lightning-fast,
again and again.
When disturbed, they coil up
into strike position,
rubbing their tough, keeled scales
together
to create a sawing sound,
hence the name.
Ignore it at your peril.
The strike comes quick,
and venom soon after.
But what makes this snake
a problem
is its proximity to humans.
The saw-scaled viper is found
across India and Pakistan,
living amongst highly populated
and remote rural farmlands.
Out here,
there is limited access
to hospitals and antivenom,
and victims often rely
on ineffective
traditional remedies.
Globally, the saw-scaled viper
is responsible
for more human deaths
than all other snake species
combined.
Many of which are children.
The viper's small size
and excellent camouflage
makes them hard to see
under leaves and grass.
And unlike the Russell's,
they don't try to flee,
or mock-charge like the king.
Instead, the saw-scaled
stands its ground,
biting at anyone and anything
that comes too close.
Ah!
Within minutes, the victim's limbs
start to swell
as the necrotic venom
breaks down blood vessels
and muscle, often leading
to unavoidable amputations.
If left untreated,
the excruciating pain
is followed by organ failure
and quite easily, death.
It's not the biggest
or the fastest,
or even the most potent,
but it lives on our doorstep,
it's notoriously aggressive,
and it strikes with relish,
which all stacks up
to make the saw-scaled viper
the deadliest snake
across the Indo-Pacific.
These snakes have a bad rap,
but their bites are in defense.
Humans aren't prey
and snakes don't actively
set out to harm us.
A life without limbs
has armed them
with an arsenal
of alternative skills
to master their environments:
chemical weaponry,
highly evolved senses,
and incredible muscle power.
Without them,
rodents would run riot,
agriculture would be plagued,
and our homes would be infested
with disease.
As much as we may fear them,
a world without snakes
would be a far more
dangerous place.